<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A proclamation by the states of the prouince of Utrecht, against certaine others of the conspirators Together with a new and full relation of the apprehension, examination, torturing, and confession of diuers of the principall conspirators, of the late intended treason against the Prince of Orange, and the state of the Vnited Prouinces. Both by letters, and other direction from the states themselues. As they were printed at Amsterdam, for Martin Iansen Brandt bookseller, dwelling by the new church at the signe of the reformed catechisme. Anno 1623.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08141</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18507.100</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24561</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103029</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838788</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838788</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3177</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08141)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3177)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1158:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A proclamation by the states of the prouince of Utrecht, against certaine others of the conspirators Together with a new and full relation of the apprehension, examination, torturing, and confession of diuers of the principall conspirators, of the late intended treason against the Prince of Orange, and the state of the Vnited Prouinces. Both by letters, and other direction from the states themselues. As they were printed at Amsterdam, for Martin Iansen Brandt bookseller, dwelling by the new church at the signe of the reformed catechisme. Anno 1623.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by J. Dawson and G. Eld] for Nathaniel Butter, Nicholas Bourne, and Thomas Archer,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>At head of title page: March 7, 1623. Numb. 21.</note>
                  <note>Printers' names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 24561.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 24561 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Maurice, --  Prince of Orange, 1567-1625 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1566-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3177:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3177:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>March 7, 1623. <hi>Numb.</hi> 21. A PROCLAMATION BY THE STATES of the Prouince of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht,</hi> againſt certaine others of the <hi>Conſpirators.</hi> Together with a new and full Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Apprehenſion, Examination, Torturing, and Confeſſion of diuers <hi>of the principall Conſpirators, of the late</hi> intended Treaſon againſt the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and the State of the <hi>Vnited Prouinces.</hi> Both by Letters, and other direction from <hi>the States themſelues.</hi> As they were Printed at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> for <hi>Martin Ian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Brandt</hi> Bookeſeller, dwelling by the new Church at the ſigne of the reformed Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſme. <hi>Anno</hi> 1623.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Nathaniel Butter, Nicholas Bourne,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Archer.</hi> 1623.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:3177:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3177:2"/>
            <head>THE PROCLAMATION OF THE STATES OF the Prouince of <hi>Vtrecht, againſt</hi> the Conſpirators.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Auritius</hi> by the Grace of God, Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> Count of <hi>Naſſaw, Meurs, Buren,</hi> &amp;c. Marquis of <hi>Camp-veere,</hi> and <hi>Fluſhing,</hi> Lord and Baron of <hi>Breda Dieſt,</hi> &amp;c. Gouernour or Deputie of <hi>Holland, Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>Vtrecht,</hi> with the States of the Land of <hi>Vtrecht,</hi> ſend to all them which ſhall ſee or heare theſe preſentes read, greeting.</p>
            <p>Seeing there is of Late diſcouered an abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, and moſt wicked Conſpiracie, againſt the State, and well-fare of the Land, and that amongſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3177:3"/>others the Inſtigators and Conductors or princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Inſtrumentes haue beene theſe following, namely <hi>Hendrick Danielſſon Slatius</hi> in former time Preacher at <hi>Bleyſwick: Adriaen Adriaenſſon van Dyck,</hi> which was here before Secretary of the ſaid place: <hi>Cornelius Gesteranus</hi> in former time Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher at <hi>Gorchum,</hi> and <hi>Cornelius Velſius,</hi> lately Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher at <hi>Rackangie,</hi> which is a village lying in the Iland of the <hi>Briel.</hi> The Sonnes of the late <hi>Barne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelt,</hi> and <hi>Adriaen Vander Duſſen</hi> of <hi>Rotterdam,</hi> are likewiſe accuſed of the crime afore ſayd, beſides many more, which are all fled intending to ſaue themſelues in <hi>Brabant,</hi> or other Countries of our Enemies, ſo that they are not eaſily to be mett withall, although their apprehenſion is much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, and greatly neceſſary for the good of theſe vnited Prouinces.</p>
            <p>So it is, that there is notice giuen by theſe preſents that whoſoeuer can reveale any one of them, or any of their complices, and aſſiſtantes which haue had a hand in this abominable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy, and cauſe them a liue to be deliuered to the Iuſtice, that he ſhall be rewarded with the ſum of 4000. Gilders, which amounte to 400. pound ſterling for each one of the perſons which are here aboue named and deſcribed, and for any other they ſhall be recompenſed with a ſumme of 600. Gilders, which amounte to 60. poundes ſtarling: And here beſides ſhall the reuealers or Informers be pardoned of this crime if they be guiltie of it: and their owne perſons and names
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3177:3"/>ſhall not be made knowne to any.</p>
            <p>We interdicte and prohibite likewiſe by theſe all manner of Perſons to lodge any of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned (which hide themſelues) or their complices, and aſſiſtantes which are culpable of this damnable and deteſtable Conſpiracy, in their houſes, or keepe, or ſuffer them in their Gardens, Ships, Boates, Haye Reekes, Barnes, or permit them to goe away with their Wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons, Horſes, Carts, Sleds, or any ſuch like ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to get away, either by Water, or by Land, vpon paine of life and goodes, and there ſhall not any fauour be ſhewed to any, although it were firſt knowne many yeares after.</p>
            <p>Furthermore ſeeing it hath appeared mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly by diuers informations, which the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners authoriſed and appointed thereunto haue receiued, that the <hi>Arminians,</hi> or the Societie of the Remonſtrants (as they inſtile them) haue in theſe Landes, a formall Court, or Colledge, wherein they meete, being alſo prouided of diuers Commiſſioners, or chiefe vndertakers and a Superintendent: likewiſe it is confeſſed, that they haue diuers Commiſſioners in euerie Towne, and Citie, to gather the moneys a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them of their owne Faction, of which they muſt make accompt to their Court where the Superintendent ſittes with the other Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. Moreouer that ſome of their ſocietie had written to ſome of their Preachers in theſe Landes, that they maruailed mightily that ſome
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3177:4"/>of them mayntained that their ſocietie might not right their cauſe by the way of violence: And they had therefore conſulted vpon this point at their meeting, or Court, where they iudged that the ſayd way could not be tryed without indangering the Country to her vtter deſtruction and ruine, neuertheleſſe conſidering that they could not mend themſelues (as they thought) in any other manner of wayes, and ſuſpecting their Confraters, or Brothers to ſmell of <hi>Anabaptiſme,</hi> or <hi>Memnoniſme,</hi> (knowing that their opinion was hurtfull to their deſſignes) they reiected them: Whereby, as likewiſe by that which is alreadie diſcouered of the aforeſayd abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and moſt deteſtable Conſpiracy, as alſo, by the Enterpriſes, and Machinations of the hidden Preachers, aboue mentioned, and diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of their Societie, it appeareth euidently, that they haue vſed all kind of ſiniſter practiſes and deuiſes, to diſturbe againe not onely the Church and State, but likewiſe to cauſe in theſe Countries an ineuitable or vnauoydable bath of blood, and to deſtroy theſe Prouinces afterwards by Incendiaries, or firers which ſhould ſet ſeuerall places on fire, whereupon (when the Countrey ſhould haue beene in this confuſion and perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itie) would our Enemie, haue aſſaulted vs, and inuaded the Country to make himſelfe Maſter of it, which he hath not beene able to doe (God be praiſed within the ſpace of theſe laſt 50. yeeres and more, although hee imployed to the ſayd
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3177:4"/>purpoſe great Armies, and charges, as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared likewiſe of late within theſe laſt two yeares.</p>
            <p>Seeing alſo that a great while ſince it is perceiued, that diuers <hi>Arminian</hi> preachers which were here tofore baniſhed, and led out of theſe Vnited Prouinces, haue emboldened themſelues to returne hither againe (in ſuch manner that there hath beene foure and twentie of them at once at <hi>Vtrecht</hi>) againſt the Proclamations of the High and Mighty Lords, the States Generall of the Vnited Prouinces, and goe diſguiſed with ſtrange habits in the Vnited Prouinces, and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally in this Prouince of <hi>Vtrecht,</hi> as well in the Citie, as the other Townes and Villages thereof, conuerſing and walking there both day and night: Keeping alſo ſecret meetings, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenticles, in which they make euen their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, (which are prohibited by the State) and prouoke there, and inſtigate the good Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the Vnited Prouinces, and eſpecially them of the Citie, the Townes, and the Lands of <hi>Vtrecht,</hi> to factions and commotions, and diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: as likewiſe to the diſobedience of their Superiours and Magiſtrates: In ſuch manner, that (which is great pitty) there are found ſome of their faction and Society, that haue loſt the one which they did beare in former time to the Almighty, their Countrey, and Countri-men, (before this <hi>Arminian</hi> Faction or Sect (rather) aroſe, liuing then Peaceably with their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours)
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3177:5"/>and haue forgotten themſelues ſo farre, that they haue beene plotters and chiefe worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters of this moſt wicked and abominable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy, and made it ready to the execution, which had happened aſſuredly, if the mercifull God had not ſtopt their proceedings, through his infinite wiſedome, and cauſed it to be reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in good time.</p>
            <p>So it is that wee inſiſting vpon that which is aforeſayd, prohibite moreouer (according to the tenour of the two former Proclamations of the generall States, one of them was dated the third of Iuly, 1619. the other the firſt of Febru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary, <hi>Anno</hi> 1620. and the reſolutions, and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations made ſince vpon them) expreſſely, any manner of perſons whatſoeuer, to appeare (vnder what pretext or colour ſoeuer) at any of thoſe meetings, and conuenticles aforeſayd, neither in the Citie, nor Townes, nor Lands of this Prouince, or to doe or ſay any thing which might in any manner of wayes preiudice the Land, or the Gouernment: vpon the paines ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the Proclamations aforeſayd, beſides they ſhall bee accounted as perturbators of the State, and ſhall be puniſhed according to their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and as the caſe ſhall require. Likewiſe wee charge that none ſhall preſume to lodge any of the baniſhed Preachers afore mentioned, which are alſo led out of the Country, nor any of their young propounders, or other which doe not ſtick to cauſe prohibited meetings, to preach, reade, or exhort in the ſame without permiſſion.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3177:5"/>As likewiſe to adminiſter the Sacraments, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Eccleſiaſticall functions, nor cauſe or ſuffer them to come in their houſes, gardens, hay-reekes, barnes, ſhips, boats, wagons, carts, or ſleds: nor to hide them any where, be it by water or by land, vpon paine of baniſhment, or otherwiſe (as the fault ſhall deſerue) to be puniſhed, without that any long time ſhall excuſe them although it were many yeares ſince diſcouered.</p>
            <p>And becauſe ſuch perſons may be the better re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed and taken, they which ſhall diſcouer them, (which are here laſt of all mentioned) ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded with the ſumme of 300. Gilders, which are 30 pounds ſterling, and ſhall receiue them of the Country or State: and if they be guilty themſelues they ſhall be pardoned, promiſing moreouer, that their perſons or names ſhall not be diſcouered. For wee haue iudged with a generall voyce this to be conuenient, and a fit remedy to preuent all fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Conſpiracies and wicked Machinations, and to aduance the welfare and preſeruation of theſe Lands, and their inhabitants.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the contents hereof may well be obſerued and kept, and that none might pretent ignorance, We haue giuen order that this preſent Proclamation ſhall be publiſhed in all vſuall pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as the cuſtome is, and command hereby the Preſident, and the Councell of <hi>Vtrecht,</hi> as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe all Officers, Iuſtices, and miniſters of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, whom this may concerne, to proceede a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the offenders, and cauſe likewiſe to bee
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3177:6"/>proceeded againſt them without any connivency, ſauour, or diſſimulation to the contrary.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Giuen at Vtrecht,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 14. <hi>day of February, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the new ſtyle. Anno</hi> 1623.</date>
               </dateline> Vpon the margine was written,
<signed>Dirick van Eck. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</signed> Lower ſtood,
<signed>By the order of the aforeſaid Lords the States.</signed> And was ſubſcribed,
<signed>Ant: van Hilten.</signed>
               <signed>Vpon the Margine was the Seale of the ſaid States in red waxe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:3177:6"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From the Hage, </hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Febr.</hi> 8. 1623.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>LOuing Friend: knowing that there are diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed amongſt you ſtrange ſpeeches of the Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners here lately taken, I would not forbeare to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe you the truth of the matter.</p>
            <p>The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> being two dayes agoe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the afternoone, at <hi>Ryſwyck,</hi> there came three or foure Saylers which deſired to ſpeake with his Excellency, and hauing gotten acceſſe to his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, they related, that they were asked at <hi>Rotter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> whether they would be imployed in a ſeruice for the good of theſe Countries, and were alſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed great reward therefore.</p>
            <p>They confeſſed moreouer, that they had accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſaid ſeruice, and had receiued certaine mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney thereupon, and that they were ſent afterwards to the <hi>Hage,</hi> where they deliuered two dayes agoe their fire-workes and other things, at a houſe (vnto which they were directed) called the little foole in the Achterom, which is a ſtreet. And that they had ſpoken there with the party vnto whom they were directed to receiue further inſtruction: but he had not told the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the ſame time, what they ſhould doe, wiſhing them onely to goe on to the buſineſſe with a good courage, and promiſing that the next day the matter ſhould be laid open vnto them.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:3177:7"/>
            <p>They told moreouer, that they got of them at that inſtant certaine Duch Riders of 21. ſhillings ſterling a peece, which they ſhewed alſo to the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and ſaid that their great liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty made them to miſtruſt the goodneſſe of this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, and cauſed them to ſuſpect ſome treaſon or Conſpiracy.</p>
            <p>Hereupon the Prince commanded them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to the <hi>Hage,</hi> and to come towards euening to him at his Palace. Which they did, and infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med his Excellency fully of all the buſineſſe.</p>
            <p>Whereupon he ſent preſently for the Preſident, and the Councell of State, who forthwith (after ſome deliberation) ſent the Atturney or Fiſcall of the Court, with the Prouoſt Marſhall, to the houſe or Inne aforeſaid, where they found the perſons by them deſcribed, and the man which paid them the money aforeſaid, whom they carried inſtantly to the Court, and examined them.</p>
            <p>The Towneſmen and the Souldiers within were preſently commanded to keepe ſtrong watches euery where, and to ſtop all paſſages that no body ſhould come away without leaue. But it was not poſſible for them to preuent it, ſeeing there are no walls about the <hi>Hage.</hi> They ſearched alſo after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Helmet (an Inne) about the Waggons which goe to <hi>Harlem,</hi> and when they asked for the man with his Trunks, the owner thereof went ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily vp into a chamber where it ſtood, and opening it, he tooke ſome things thereour, and leauing it open, came downe in great haſte, and got out of the houſe, ſeeing that there was a Serjeant which
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3177:7"/>told to the reſt, that he was an honeſt man, and that he had knowne him many yeares agoe.</p>
            <p>When the Fiſcall asked the Hoſte whether there was not a man with a trunke in his houſe: he anſwered, no: But ſeeing they found afterwards the trunke, (open with diuers piſtols and other things, as it was left by the owner) when they ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the houſe, the Hoſte was taken priſoner, though the owner, the former Secretary of <hi>Bleyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke</hi> had made an eſcape, as is aforeſaid, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were examined the ſame night, and he which payed the money to the Mariners confeſſed that there was one dwelling at <hi>Rotterdam</hi> which had ſet him on work, and hauing told his name and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed his perſon, there went, about foure of the clocke in the morning, two Councellors of State with diuers others to find him out, but he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted thence, &amp; it is thought that the late Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Bleyſwick</hi> who was eſcaped had giuen him notice of the diſcouering of their conſpiracy.</p>
            <p>The examinations of the priſoners haue laſted yeſterday, and this night and day, but their confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions are kept as yet very ſecret: there are found in the meane time many piſtols, ſwords and daggers in the truncke aforeſaid, and in the other Inne, and I haue ſeene ſome of them at the Court.</p>
            <p>To day had the Preachers order to giue God thankes in their prayers for the diſcouering of this abhominable conſpiracy of the enemies of the State.</p>
            <p>The Mariners which haue reuealed this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, are glad that they haue cleared their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3177:8"/>and caſt this burthen off their necks, making good cheare at the Caſtelayn of the Court his houſe.</p>
            <p>I heare at this inſtant that there is now to bee made another ſearch: of the ſucceſſe I will aduiſe you with the next, if God giue me leaue.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From Amſterdam, </hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Febr.</hi> 28. 1623.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>Yeſterday were 4. of the conſpiracy executed at the <hi>Hage,</hi> one of them was beheaded and quarte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, the other three were onely beheaded: to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row we hope to get here the Copies of their ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences. The principall and the richer ſort are as yet kept in priſon, but it is generally reported that they ſhall follow the other very ſpeedily.</p>
            <p>They haue confeſſed that they would haue mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered firſt of all the Prince of <hi>Orange:</hi> ſecondly, changed the gouernment and Religion: thirdly, that they had correſpondency and intelligence with the enemies: fourthly, that they would haue ſet on fire ſeuerall houſes and townes.</p>
            <p>Laſt Sunday, paſt through this City certaine Souldiers of <hi>Emden,</hi> which brought thence theſe following priſoners; <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Ian Blancert,</hi> and one <hi>William Pertii,</hi> carrying them by the way of <hi>Harlem</hi> towards the <hi>Hage.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:3177:8"/>
            <head>A RELATION, OR The Light of February: Wherein is to be ſeene, <hi>The ſtrange and abominable Conſpiracy which was intended againſt the vnited Prouinces, and the Inhabitants therein: Reuealed by theſe foure ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men:</hi> Iohn Engelen, Iohn Faes, Ieroen Ewoutſzon, Pieter Ianſsen Broeck.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T ſeemeth that the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hath beene pleaſed many times to defend or preſerue his Church not onely by meanes of the ſimple, but euen alſo by the actions of her owne enemies, as you may perceiue by this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Relation. And it is very well knowne to the Inhabitants of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, what kind of fellowes our Mariners are for the moſt part, and principally theſe 4, which diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the treaſon, here before mentioned, to be very ſtout and reſolute, and ſtained moreouer with the Arminian doctrine, as all the reſt of the conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, but I will not ſay that they are all ſtained which haue conuerſed with them, with ſuch a foule ſpot, as ſhall appeare by theſe and other good Patriots or well-willers of their Country.</p>
            <p>But to come to the matter: It is to be obſerued
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3177:9"/>that the eldeſt of theſe foure Mariners was called (by a nicke name) <hi>Light,</hi> amongſt the common people, which ſeemed to preſage ſome thing, if the Prognoſtication had beene made before the effect appeared: but to leaue all friuolous things behind, and to relate ſhortly that which is paſt in theſe parts of the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> concerning the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy aforementioned.</p>
            <p>The 4. of February, in the yeere 1623. came to <hi>Rotterdam</hi> a ſtrange Monſter, in the ſhape of the former Secretary of <hi>Bleyſwyck,</hi> hauing his belly fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with ranke poyfon, as ſhall be publiſhed after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward by authority of the State to all the world: This wicked fellow who (as he thought) could al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his mouth &amp; face into ſuch countenance as he pleaſed, and change his voice as he liſted, was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with one of the Mariners aforeſaid, but the Mariner could not feele preſently with his woollen gloues what he carried vnder his cloak, as he did afterwards (by the grace of God) when his hands were naked. He told in the beginning to the Mariner, that it was a braue enterpriſe, &amp; tending to the good of the Common-wealth, but (as hee ſaid) it muſt be kept ſecret, and the reward would aſſwage or ſweeten the labour and pains, and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him therefore to find out three other luſty and reſolute Saylers as he was himſelfe, which he did at an inſtant, (ſeeing they know one another, and can certifie whom they dare truſt with their liues, and will ſtand for a man when occaſion ſhall ſerue) and brought them to him; where after ſome ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches betwixt them, the foure Mariners yeelded to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3177:9"/>their employment in the ſayd ſeruice. About the ſame time there came another (whom they neuer ſaw before) which after ſome conference gaue them 300. Gilders (which amount to 30. Pound ſterling) a piece aforehand, onely vpon hope of good ſucceſſe, which pleaſed the Mariners excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding well, and made them grow hot to the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: Hee added moreouer that after the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe was performed they ſhould want neither goods nor money, and ſhould each one of them beſides be honoured with an office. After theſe faire promiſes made vnto the Mariners, the other two told them where they ſhould receiue diuers Piſtols, beſides gunpowder, and Lead, or Bullets, with great ſtore of Stillettos or murdering Dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and other ſuch like things to pierce a harneſſe of proofe withall, and deſired them to bring them in ſeuerall trunkes to a certaine Inne at the <hi>Hage,</hi> which they performed with all poſſible ſpeed, and diligence, for they packt theſe things ſecretly vp in trunkes, and cauſed them in their company the 5. of February to bee carried from <hi>Rotterdam</hi> to <hi>Delft,</hi> and thence towards the <hi>Hage,</hi> where they brought them to the appointed Inne called the Helmet, and found there at the ſame inſtant their Maſter (which ſet them on work at the beginning) who bade them welcome, and made them good cheare.</p>
            <p>In the meane time had he (who payed them the money) hired likewiſe foure other couragious and luſty Mariners, and had ſent them with the like in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments and commodities put in trunkes as the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3177:10"/>other, through the ſame paſſage towards the <hi>Hage,</hi> &amp; charged the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to meet at an Inne called the little Foole, (which they did) and were there well recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and entertained with drinke and meat.</p>
            <p>The ſixt of this Moneth (O happy day) beganne the Mariners aforeſaid to ſuſpect the buſineſſe, (without queſtion through the inſpiration of the Almighty) and to confer one with another about it, and concluded amongſt themſelues, that they would not enter any further into the ſaid buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, beleeuing it to be a foule peece of worke: And reſolued thereupon that two of them ſhould goe inſtantly to the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> to certifie his Excellency of the caſe, and to learne whether they were employed in the ſeruice of the Country or not. Comming with all poſſible ſpeed to the Court in the <hi>Hage,</hi> they vnderſtood that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was gone to <hi>Ryſwyck,</hi> (where ſome of his Horſe are kept) they went thither preſently with their tarred apparell, &amp; ſheaths of horne for their kniues, and other things, as the Saylers vſe to weare in the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> and talking amongſt themſelues along the way, the time ſeemed very ſhort vnto them at their arriuall: And amongſt the reſt, they conferred together in what manner, and with what countenance they ſhould ſpeake to the Prince his Excellency.</p>
            <p>When they were at the Stable of the Prince, they ſaw there diuers Lacquies and Yeomen of the Prince his Guard, and told them that they would faine ſpeake a word or two with his Excellency; but no body ſeemed to giue greatly eare vnto
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3177:10"/>them, neuertheleſſe there was one of the Lacquies, who laughing, accepted to tell the Prince of them and their deſire, ſuſpecting that they had ſome ſtrange toy or thing to ſhew to his Excellency; who ſent them word backe againe by the Lacquy, that he would heare them as ſoone as he came out of his ſtable: whereupon they anſwered, that they would ſpeak with his Excellency about a buſineſſe that concerned mightily his own perſon, and that there was perhaps danger in delay, (as the Ciuill Lawyers ſay) <hi>Periculum in mora:</hi> The Prince (who hath loued continually the Mariners) vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this, cauſed them inſtantly to come to him, where they made the beſt reuerence they could af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their owne manner, and reuealed all the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnto him. Now you may gueſſe what the Prince thought of it, hearing of an enterpriſe of which he knew not himſelfe: he commanded the Mariners to returne to the Court, by the way of <hi>Vorburg,</hi> which is a village about the <hi>Hage,</hi> and rode himſelfe with all ſpeed to the Court, where he communicated inſtantly this matter with the States. Hereupon was preſently giuen order that the two Innes here before mentioned, ſhould be ſearched inſtantly, and that all them which were within the two Innes ſhould be ceaſed vpon, vntill ſuch time as the heads and complices of this wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked onterpriſe ſhould be found out. They got the money maſter or Purſer, (who payed the Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners) at the Inne called the little Foole, the reſt which were in the houſe are likewiſe apprehended, and I cannot heare as yet that any one of them is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3177:11"/>ſet at liberty. At the other Inne (where the Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary of <hi>Bleyſwick</hi> eſcaped) were euen alſo diuers apprehended, but they are all diſmiſt, ſeeing they were found innocent and cleare of this buſineſſe. All the inſtruments aforeſaid which were found in the two Innes, were likewiſe carried away by the Officers of the Court.</p>
            <p>Concerning the Mariners, they were 9. dayes kept in the houſe of the Keeper or Caſtelain of the Court, vntil the States knew by examination that they were not guilty, and had behaued themſelues as true Patriots and well-willers of the Country ought to doe, and diſcharged their conſciences.</p>
            <p>This night and the next day commanded the States ſtrong watches to be kept, as well of the Townſmen, as of the Souldiers about the <hi>Hage,</hi> and the paſſages to goe thence: And they cauſed likewiſe a Proclamation to be publiſhed and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as we haue heard before.</p>
            <p>The next day being Wedneſday, vpon the 8. of this Moneth, was the faſting and prayer day kept, whereof the States had warned the Country fourteen dayes before. This alteration ſeemed to cauſe a new zeale amongſt the inhabitants, that all the Churches were packt vp ſo full, as the like was not ſeene by any man liuing.</p>
            <p>About the euening came the Hangman into the <hi>Hage,</hi> to put ſome of the apprehended to the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. The ſame day were likewiſe three of <hi>Barne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velts</hi> ſeruants taken priſoners, and the houſe of the widow of <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Oldenbarnevelt</hi> as likewiſe that of <hi>Renier</hi> of <hi>Oldenbarnevelt</hi> his ſonne guarded by
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3177:11"/>certaine officers of the Court.</p>
            <p>The 9. day of this Moneth were yet ſome at the <hi>Hage</hi> apprehended, and there came newes that two were taken at <hi>Rotterdam,</hi> and that ſome were fled thence, whereupon the Country was much per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed.</p>
            <p>The ſame day there came alſo tidings from <hi>Harlem,</hi> that there was made a great hole in the walls of the priſon by ſome which were without, with a great augre, iuſt vpon the roome in which two Arminian Preachers were put about three weekes agoe, becauſe they were come into the Dominion of the States, out of which they were baniſhed.</p>
            <p>The 10. and 11. day of this Moneth, were in all the Cities and Townes of the Vnited Prouinces the Proclamations of the States concerning this Conſpiracy publiſhed, &amp; euery where great paines were taken to apprehend the Authors and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices thereof. In thoſe dayes was the Lord <hi>van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Mylen</hi> ſent for to come into the <hi>Hage,</hi> where he came freely, and is lodged now at the houſe of the Keeper of the Court, whereby it ſeemeth that hee is not ſuſpected.</p>
            <p>The 12. day of this Moneth when it was night, there were two poore Boers which ſaw <hi>Adriaen Adriaenſſon van Dyck,</hi> the former Secretary of <hi>Bleyſwyck,</hi> wherevpon they went purpoſely to the Mayor of the place, who tooke him afterwards: whereupon the Boers got within few dayes the moneyes promiſed by the Proclamation of the States, for the diſcouering of him, namely 4000.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3177:12"/>Gilders, which amount to 400. pounds ſterling.</p>
            <p>The 14. of this Moneth, the fore-mentioned <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>driaen Adriaenſſon van Dyck</hi> ſent for ſome of his Children and Kindred (a little before the Officers came to him out of the <hi>Hage</hi>) and confeſſed vnto them that he had deſerued death, and curſed migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily the Arminian Preachers which ſeduced him, hee was yet the ſame day brought to the priſon of the <hi>Hage</hi> by the Officers which came for him from the Court.</p>
            <p>This day were the Sailers (which had vntill that time made good cheare at the houſe of the keeper of the Court) ſet at liberty, and each one of them was honoured of his Excellency with a peece of gold whereon was the Picture and Armes of the Prince with his Deuice, worth about 80. Gilders, which amount to 8. pounds ſterling, as likewiſe with a ſiluerd Sword for each of them. The States moreouer cauſed to each of them to be giuen 600. Gilders which amount to 60. pounds ſterling, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides a monethly penſion of 16. Gilders, or 32. ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings ſterling, during their liues: granting them moreouer their Letters of recommendation to the Court of Admiralty, for the firſt offices (of which they be capable) that ſhall fall. Whereupon they returned with great contentment to <hi>Rotterdam,</hi> and told their friends their fortune, and cloathed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues there in gray ſutes of cloath, and bought there for their own wearing gray hats, with golden bands, as if they had bin Sea-Captains already.</p>
            <p>The ſame day were the bels of the Town houſe of the <hi>Hage</hi> rung, whereupon the two ſonnes of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3177:12"/>
               <hi>Barnevelt</hi> were warned to appeare within the ſpace of 14. daies; and to anſwer for themſelues vpon paine of their baniſhment, &amp; confiſcation of their goods, according to the Lawes and cuſtome of the Country.</p>
            <p>The 15. day foure Citizens were apprehended at <hi>Leyden</hi> about this Conſpiracy, and it was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued that ſome of their conſorts were fled.</p>
            <p>The 16. of this Moneth was at the <hi>Hage</hi> a ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour that both the ſonnes of <hi>Barneuelt</hi> were ſeene at <hi>Scheuelingen</hi> about the Sea-coaſt, with a skipper of their acquaintance who dwelt there, wherupon his Wife was apprehended in the abſence of her husband and carryed to the <hi>Hage,</hi> where ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed vpon examination that her husband depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the night before from his houſe with them: &amp; ſearch being made, it was found out preſently that they went from <hi>Scheuelingen</hi> to <hi>Berckerhey, Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyck, Noortwyck, Santvoort, Wyck op Zee,</hi> along a ditch towards the Sea, which is called the <hi>Honds<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſh,</hi> and came thence into the Iſland of <hi>Texel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 17. day of this Moneth was the town-houſe of <hi>Rotterdam</hi> fired very earely in the morning, at which time the Cutler afore mentioned got away among the people which came to quench the fire, he was taken, becauſe hee had ſold diuers Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and armes to the Conſpirators. The other, namely the Tinker was diſmiſt by the Lords, ſeeing there was at that time yet nothing found out wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they could charge him.</p>
            <p>The Cutler went to diuers of his acquaintance, but no man would receiue him, and ſeeing hee is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3177:13"/>ſtill abſent there is promiſed a ſumme of mone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to them that ſhall cauſe him to be apprehended.</p>
            <p>The 18. of this Moneth was the eldeſt ſonne of <hi>Barnevelt</hi> taken in the Iſland of <hi>Texel,</hi> with the skipper aforeſaid, and one of his men.</p>
            <p>The 19. being the next day, he was brought to the <hi>Hage</hi> and put in priſon, where he was examined ſince, but we cannot heare as yet any thing of his confeſſion.</p>
            <p>The 20. of this Moneth were all the priſoners which were taken about this Conſpiracy exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Iuſtices of the Court.</p>
            <p>The 21. were at <hi>Ouwerſchic,</hi> a village, yet two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther taken of this Conſpiracy, namely <hi>Dauid Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renwinder</hi> Secretary in former time of <hi>Berckel,</hi> and the Boer which lodged him. They were carried likewiſe the ſame day to the priſon which is in the <hi>Hage,</hi> where there are (maſters and ſeruants) at leaſt twenty, apprehended for this Conſpiracy.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
